[SPEAKER_00]: We received a few questions through various mediums.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a sort of common thing as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: People wonder how to start practicing.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the best way to begin your practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, you're just interested in Buddhism.
[SPEAKER_00]: You read something that you found inspirational.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you go about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I think this should be probably more like something for beginners to listen to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the important thing is you don't stop reading, you don't stop learning about the actual suttas and what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are whole different layers of understanding to it, in a sense that first time you read a sutta, you'll be inspired, it makes sense and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if you keep the practice going and then you get back to that sutta at some later stage,
[SPEAKER_00]: You get more out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize that your previous understanding was correct, but now you just kind of went even a step further.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, within the original understanding, you now understood more.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that kind of inevitably let you let you think that... why stop there?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if next time you come back to it, it's a good chance you'll find even more in the same sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's important to recognize that
[SPEAKER_00]: You can never know too much, in terms of the Buddhist instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: The more you know, the greater likelihood, if you're applying yourself correctly as well, with the proper base of virtue and so on, so the more you know, the greater likelihood is that you will get to discern those things within your experience, because you have obviously a wider range of tools that you can then recognize, as opposed to if you just have one.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's important to practice learning, but in order for those things to apply, sense restraint and virtue need to be fully established.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like the main point, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, often people differentiate between, like, a layperson and a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, that there's a difference in terms of the, you know, external statement and the lifestyle.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, really, the difference is whether a person lives with centrality or without centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether he lives with with sense desires or he practices sense restraint in regard to... That's where the difference is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, most commonly, yes, a layperson is the person who lives with centrality and usually monks are the ones practicing restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's important to recognize this, to differentiate this, because... See, if somebody stays a lay person, for whatever reason they have, that does not automatically mean you should not practice sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it is somehow taken in that sort of intentionally ambiguous manner whereby, oh, I cannot be a monk because I have to look after my mother.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by default, that means I can also engage in sensuality because I have a good reason to not be a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's completely wrong thinking, basically, and it's a... it's a... they're two separate things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you... you want to pursue a lifestyle of a monk or a lifestyle of a layperson, that's one decision.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you make another decision on top of it, to not practice sensory strength, or to practice it only... practice it only partially.
[SPEAKER_00]: That has nothing to do with your choice of being a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you are responsible for, basically, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Confusing these things and then, obviously, acting out of sensuality towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Somebody can become a monk and then expect the circumstance and the environment to do the restraint for him and make no effort internally to uproot sensuality on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, although they're not engaging in sensual activities with their body, they're still very much within the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're basically living almost like a layperson who is not restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's also another reason why this is important to differentiate is because, yes, there were suttas with the Buddha's
[SPEAKER_00]: The lay people understood the dhamma, but they did not understand the dhamma on account of the sensual life.
[SPEAKER_00]: They might have... whenever they stayed a lay person and not gone forth out of faith in the Buddhist teaching that they acquired, it was always rooted in some necessity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, they had to look after their children or the mother.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would die if they leave.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it wasn't even like, oh, they'll be upset with me.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's like, if I'm not there looking after them, they're done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they had, like, protecting other people's lives, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why they couldn't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, they were practicing as lay people.
[SPEAKER_00]: They did not take my duty towards my family or whatever to be the excuse that I can also live a sensual life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to understand a dhamma, you need to live withdrawn from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is easier to do if you're not a lay person.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... if you choose to be a layperson, means you're adding to yourself another extra task on top of the task of understanding dhamma, which is...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensory restraint amidst the environment that's completely opposite of the sensory restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's very hard to sustain that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why people would then tend to avoid or turn a blind eye to the fact that they're responsible for the choice of their environment, more or less, and then just go with it, go with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And
[SPEAKER_00]: If people think that five precepts are enough to practice the dhamma, well, those were not really enough even back in the Buddha's day.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha taught the five precepts to people not as a basis of understanding the, like, right view, but more as a basis of differentiating human from an animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basis of good rebirth, basis of eventual wisdom through that initial sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you have people who don't even keep the five precepts and hope they can practice dhamma or have a view that they are practicing dhamma at the same time, that is simply impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's utter contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sense restraint is not... it's not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can choose to be whatever you like, but you cannot choose to
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot be restrained or not and think you can practice dhamma at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rather, you can choose it, but you will be living a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whenever the people who are not monks understood the dhamma back in the day, it's because they were withdrawn from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if they decided to go back to sensuality afterwards, it has to be done at the expense of the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you cannot practice and be in sensuality at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might be content with what you understood,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then not make the further effort, as people would get complacent, and that was happening even to the monks in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when the Buddha would urge, or even tell them off quite severely, almost like verbally abuse them, because he said, I know that you can do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was to Venerable Ananda, when he said that, I will not treat you like a like a potter treats his precious clay pot.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll smash you with stone, verbally, so to speak, and then the solid core will stand that test.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because Ananda was sort of postponing the work that he still needed to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: He already had the right view, but he was distracting himself with seemingly important duties, such as sewing robes and getting together with the monks and teaching them this and doing that, and then the Buddha really, really told him off.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, you can get complacent with your attainment, but in order to develop the attainment, you cannot start from the complacency.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, I am fine as I am, in whatever environment I am, and sensuality is not a problem for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality is always a problem, because it's a direct contradiction to the principles of the dhamma that needs to be understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't have it both ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like that
[SPEAKER_00]: That sutta where the two friends go to the mountain, one of them stays at the bottom, the other one climbs up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And shouts back down to this one and says like, wow, the view from here and I see all these pools and gardens and other... And the man from below says, no, I don't see any of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I disagree with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: I, I, I... like, you're not, you know, what you're saying is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the man comes down, grabs him by the arm and drags him back up and shows him that same view and then says, oh, yes, truly, look at these beautiful, delightful sights and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point is, you have to recognize that your criteria
[SPEAKER_00]: For what is right, what is possible, is not necessarily correct, because you might be well at the bottom of the mountain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're refusing to climb for whatever reason, and then, refusing to climb for whatever reason, you use an excuse to indulge with whatever it's at the bottom of that mountain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, it doesn't matter whether you wear robes or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Matters whether you accept sensuality on the mental level, whether you're physically withdrawn from it, and whether you're practicing sense restraint for the point of... for the goal of overcoming it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, as we said many times in other talks, you need to take responsibility for your choices, because otherwise, you won't feel responsible for engaging in sensuality, because you don't... you don't... you haven't taken the responsibility for choosing to not climb the mountain, in terms of the practice,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not to go in the higher environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's fine, but that now means you have to be twice as careful at the bottom of that mountain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not, oh, because I'm not at the top of the mountain, I can fully indulge and engage with whatever comes my way here at the bottom of the mountain.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, that's a completely separate thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a completely another extra layer on top of already something which is already a compromise.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start a practice by learning.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you start a practice by fully integrating and realizing that there is absolutely no chance of understanding anything that's been learned, unless there is a proper virtue developed, proper establishment, proper sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that means celibate, that means moderation and restraint in eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: More often than not, that doesn't mean only five precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Five precepts will make you a good person.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, five precepts are not negotiable basis for a human life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't want to be like an animal, mentally have a mind of an animal, five precepts are the threshold below which you cannot go.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yes, they will offer an improvement to an unrestrained mind, but if you really want to understand the dhamma, this and the sign of your mind, the necessary condition for sotāpatti, for the right view, it needs to be more.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind needs to be fully withdrawn from that sensuality, needs to be celibate, needs to not entertain things throughout the day of central nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you can sustain that level in the environment of the, you know, outer world, at the bottom of the mountain,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's fine, but it was hard to sustain back in the Buddha's day, without all the quick, instantaneous access to distractions and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And today, it's going to take some serious willpower.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you were to possess that willpower, there would be nothing binding you to the bottom of that mountain anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would overcome it and go to a better place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even back in the day, as I said, you know, like Gautika the potter, who was an anāgāmī, you know, they were not anāgāmīs because... sorry, they were not celibate because they were anāgāmīs.
[SPEAKER_00]: They became anāgāmīs because they were celibate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lay people, but celibate.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only reason he didn't go forth with the previous Buddha was because he was, eh... elderly parents.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would die without him.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were completely dependent on him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same with the lady, I forgot her name, whose son got falsely imprisoned and murdered.
[SPEAKER_00]: And while her husband was alive, before that, when she understood the dhamma, you know, she was a dutiful wife and everything else, but he passed away, and then she was just a fully celibate, withdrawn mentally from sensuality, became anāgāmī, established herself in jhānas and all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, you can be a lay person and have all the jhānas and stuff, if you're fully celibate and withdrawn from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why I say, usually the people have problem with this, is because for them automatically it's implicit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I have a good reason to be a layperson, which means I'm justified in engaging with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, learn, practice sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, you have to withdraw yourself to some extent from company and environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then things in the suttas, that seemingly sound like some old folklore stories and stuff, will definitely start making more and more sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will be verifying it for yourself, because your liability to suffering will be diminishing.